## Ieva Rozentāle

Resume

#### PERSONAL DETAILS

M (TW): +

M (NL): +31 629620649 M (LV): +371 26517262 E: <u>i.rozentale@uva.nl</u>

### **AREAS OF EXPERTISE**

Business models
Strategic management
Innovation management
Paradoxical decision-making
Qualitative and quantitative
research
Qualitative Comparative
Analysis
Placemaking
Urban design and planning
Community development
Entrepreneurship
Creative industries
Creative cities
Service firms

# **SUMMARY**

My professional experience and interests combine strategic management, particularly in beyond-profit settings, with topics related to creativity, design, sustainability, and urban planning. In my PhD project, I studied how creative service firms manage conflicting goals through business model design. I have worked on placemaking and projects that involve using creativity and community development as tools for solving complex urban and organizational problems in a more sustainable and responsible manner. I lecture and consult on these topics. I am fascinated by research methods and data science.

# RELEVANT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Researcher Mindworks

2018 - Present

Greenpeace East Asia (TW)

*Mindworks* is the cognitive lab of Greenpeace, using insights from cognitive sciences to support GP campaigns in:

- capacity building through experience and learning design
- campaign design for mindset shifts
- research, impact measurement and monitoring

## PhD Candidate

2013 - 2018

Amsterdam Business School, University of Amsterdam (NL) Research project "The Battle of The Souls: Cultural and business orientations of creative firms and their effect on business models, growth and internationalization"

Co-founder 2014 - Present

*nēbetjā, placemaking research and consultancy* (LV) Examples of projects completed:

- Redevelopment of an old factory into a creative cluster (strategy and implementation plan, community activation)
- Development strategy for a common identity, economy and public space of a new parish after an administrative reform
- Rebranding and implementation strategy of an ethnographic museum into a community and skill development center

# **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS**

Erasmus University Rotterdam (NL)

2010-2012

MA Cultural Economics and Cultural Entrepreneurship

Thesis: "Beyond Mapping – Understanding Creative Industries in Post-Command Economy Cities. The case of Riga." (Cum Laude)

University of Latvia & Urban Institute (LV) 2012 Urban Studies and Planning, 6 weeks intensive course

Latvian Academy of Culture (LV)

2006 - 2010

Bachelor Intercultural Relations, specialisation France

Thesis: "The Diplomatic Relations between Latvia and France during the Interwar Period." (Cum Laude)

#### **LECTURING**

University of Amsterdam

2013 - 2018

Data-Driven Business Innovation and Entrepreneurship Master theses supervision, MBA and Macro Economics Economics of Markets and Organizations

Erasmus University Rotterdam

2012 - 2013

Economics Aspects of Cultural Industries

Creative Cities

#### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

- Deichmann, D., Rozentale, I. & Baarnhoorn, R. (2017). <u>Open innovation generates great ideas, so why aren't companies adopting them?</u> *Harvard Business Review.*
- Rozentale, I. (2017, 12 October). Dealing with a paradox. *DUDE*, *2*, (4). (Magazine of the Dutch Designers Association), December, 54-57.
- Rozentale, I. (2014). Creative industries during economic recession: the case of Riga. *Regional Studies, Regional Science, 1*(1), 329-335.
- Rozentale, I., & Lavanga, M. (2014). The "universal" characteristics of creative industries revisited: The case of Riga. *City, Culture and Society*.

# **SELECTED RECENT PRESENTATIONS**

- Rozentale, I. & Deichmann, D. (2017, 25 October). Discussion session organization and presentation of research results: <u>Successfully implementing your crossover projects</u>. DRIVE, Design Research and Innovation Festival, Dutch Design Week, Eindhoven.
- Rozentale, I. (2017, 12 October). Presentation: What can placemakers learn from paradox scholars? International Placemaking Week, Pakhuis de Zwijger, Amsterdam.
- Rozentale, I. & Baalen, P. van (2017). Killing two birds with one business model: Unraveling successful configurations for achieving conflicting goals. International QCA Young Researcher Workshop, Zurich, Switzerland, December.
- Rozentale, I. (2017, July). *Designing business models for paradoxical goals: Lessons from creative service firms*. Paper presented at the 33nd EGOS Colloquium 2017, Sub-theme 09: (SWG) The Lived Experiences of Paradoxes: Passions, Defenses and Competing Demands, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- Rozentale, I. & Jong, de V. (2016, January 28). *Naar economische en maatschappelijke impact van de creatieve industrie: Opschaling?* Presentation for the Dutch Creative Council, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.
- Rozentale, I. (2015, October). (New?) Business Models for Cross-overs? Presentation for Drive Click NL Design Research and Innovation Festival for the Creative Industry, Dutch Design Week, Eindhoven, The Netherlands.
- Rozentale, I., Kinasts, J. & Jong, de V. (2015, June) *A Placemaking Approach to Creative Clusters: Towards a Practical Framework for Strategizing and Conceptualization.* Working paper presented in the International Seminar Cultural and Creative Quarters and Clusters: Developing a Global Perspective, Angers, France.

# SKILLS AND QUALIFICATIONS

*Mastering Software Development in R* (in progress, 2 out of 5 courses finished) Specialization track on Coursera by Johns Hopkins University

Qualitative Comparative Analysis and Set-Theoretic Methods

Advanced course, ECPR Winter School in Methods and Techniques, 2016, Bamberg, Germany ECPR Summer School in Methods and Techniques, 2014, Ljubljana, Slovenia

Latvian: native language

English: high proficiency (TOEFL ITB, 2010 - 105/120) French: high proficiency (graduated with level C1)

Dutch: advanced proficiency Russian: advanced proficiency

### **INTERESTS**

Sustainable urban development and related research and activism; Extreme sports, cycling, outdoors; Nature and sustainability; Zero Waste movement; Languages, art, photography, music, contemporary dance, 20<sup>th</sup> century literature;